[Music]
w
hello good evening good day everybody
wherever you are good day or good good
evening uh I hope you're all doing very
well and welcome back to the ask abijit
show the live stream episode 207
in this live stream I will take
questions from the live chat so I hope
you have your questions ready and let me
see who all is on the live stream I can
see pramesh hyper NS Akay Kar yamraj
Martian bishwajit lone Rider sha random
skull SII Jane svi saral Sharma Varun
Singh Malik Anish n nirmala parer shagun
Chopra namaskar sh shat Shas Rashid aera
Shivam goam Anish bushan babber pin
garti
Anish RK nikil Nei deep kaj ruik
ramachandra namah ram ram rushi an prash
geopolitical du hello endan surj MTI
kangay
jind K kavia bant 007 Aran Panda dungar
Singh Chan let's go prai nutan Roshan k
mammad 72 viddi Manar Hello viand Panda
geopolitical again Bob Marlins GK Rashmi
Singh pray Kumar pritam Sharma Manisha
cardoo rajit Tendulkar three idats surj
MTI Bish Sharma netian sahil Gupta rushi
shete shidi
rangat and lots and lots of other the
people uh feminist Slayer Matrix I Mar
usai golu
Dr J Shankar hello shashwat mukarji hi
rashan Singh doia NJ Chopra dianu nit
Niam rishikesh utar Yash Singh jawahar
chavada suit statement Cheryl Patel nain
Sai viori Kabir Z and everybody else
okay let me stop greeting you all at
that stage
and Deepak kaj I got your surname the
second time wrong I hope it I got right
this time okay let's get going with the
questions lots of stuff happening in the
world right now as always lots of
changes happening lots of things
happening lots of developments
geopolitical developments other
developments so uh let's let's uh cover
some of these things mlin asks a
question that has nothing to do with
geopolitics are there actually people
who have who don't have an internal
monologue how do they function is it
just cricket sounds I don't know I
believe that there are people who don't
have an internal monologue the internal
monologue is the internal commentator
passing comments always talking to
yourself that's the internal monologue
uh some people have it apparently some
people don't have it I'm not sure how
they function they do function pretty
well I'm sure I think Wolf Gang poy had
a colleague Wolf Gang poy the physicist
in the 1950s or 60s had a colleague pH
another physicist who apparently did not
have a monologue or something and they
dis coded accidentally while doing some
measurements some experimental physics
measurements Etc so people function in
different ways uh some people don't have
it apparently and it doesn't prevent
them from from functioning just as well
if not better than people who do have an
internal monologue interesting question
geopolitical du says how will Russia
react to prime minister modi's Ukraine
visit no no issues India is an
independent Sovereign Nation India has
its interests India will do what is best
in its interest and India is not going
and uh starting creating an an alliance
with Ukraine or or opposing Russia's
positions so right now Prime Minister
Modi today he visited Ukraine he met
with President zalinski the two leaders
hugged so what does this visit of Prime
Minister Modi to Ukraine
signify so uh first of
all we have to understand that there's
an element of national interest in this
matter so what is India's national
interest in visiting Ukraine in in Prime
Minister Modi visiting Ukraine just five
or six weeks after he visits Moscow in
meets with president Ukraine what does
India get out of this out of this visit
to Ukraine first of
all India probably is offering its good
offices to the world when it comes to
potentially uh taking this matter to the
negotiating table
so how does that help India if
if the war is potentially ended through
negotiations look India as we know the
economy is is of Paramount interest to
India the Indian economy India's economy
needs to grow it needs to keep growing
at a steady rate at a good rate the next
20 30 years we need that to happen now
if the rest of the world's economy is
depressed then that doesn't help India
it affects India see the entire world is
interconnected and right now the economy
of UK of Europe is greatly depressed
because of the events that are happening
in the Ukraine region right Germany's
economy entered a recession some time
ago other economies in Europe are not
doing well so if the war ends then
hopefully the European economy takes
starts taking off again to some extent
and that's overall good for India and
the rest of the
world so India is definitely capable of
mediating in this dispute let's say
India is uniquely positioned in the
world to act as a bridge between East
and West if both sides so
desire okay both sides need to desire
this so uh so prime minister modi's
visit to Ukraine is essentially a curtsy
visit see Ukraine is not a stakeholder
in this matter Ukraine is a proxy this
war that's happening is a proxy war
between Russia and the US Russia and
NATO and NATO is controlled and owned by
the US it's a proxy war and Ukraine is
the Canon F Ukraine is the proxy and
Ukraine as a nation has been devastated
by the war the Ukrainian population is
is badly skewed now because all the
young men are dying in the war you see
and Russia is going to be able to keep
keep the war going Russia is perfectly
fine with the war going as long as it it
goes on right now the war is Meandering
it's a it's a slow War situation despite
whatever little incursions happen here
and there or kurks or whatever right so
that's overall bad for the global
economy it's bad for the Indian economy
also it's it's also going to affect the
Indian economy so India can offer to
mediate and by by visiting Ukraine which
essentially is just a proxy Nation Prime
Minister Modi is signaling India's
willingness to if both sides so desire
to act as a mediator and India is is
uniquely positioned to Med to to talk to
both sides Russia as well as the West
with a great amount of comfort and Trust
because India doesn't have a horse in
this race right unlike Nations like
China
Etc so uh that's what it was that's what
this visit is it's a courtesy visit it's
it's signal to the West that in we would
be willing to offer our good offices for
mediation in case you are willing to do
so so right now the impediment towards
negotiations is the West Putin has said
multiple times many times that he wants
he's willing to negotiate he's open to
negotiations but the West doesn't want
diplomacy they want the war to continue
they have their own calculations in
agenda right uh so that's the situation
right now and that's what the visit is
about so I don't see any reason why
Prime why President Putin would be upset
with with what with this visit of Mr
Modi uh to
Ukraine
okay
um mclen says China has extradited a
couple of khalistanis really I was not
aware of that what does does that say
our relations are getting better with
China well that remains to be seen okay
I'm not aware of this particular piece
of news that they have extradited couple
of khalistanis if they have
good uh but we are definitely seeing
signs and symptoms of the relationship
may be getting on a slightly better
track okay uh and there are lots of
reasons for this and and it all goes
back to what happened recently in
Bangladesh the US engineered regime
change operation the coup that happened
in Bangladesh and the pro-india
government was was osted and a strongly
anti-india government has come to power
uh and there's also a civil war
situation in Myanmar right now
like I've spoken many times before and
that essentially is is is a disaster for
China because the Myanmar government the
military government was pro-china now
they control less than 50% of of the
territory of Burma and the rebels who
control the territory that the
government has lost are all pro us so
there's this project K that I've spoken
about right project cooky land the the
the project to create a new artificial
deao Christian Christian defacto Nation
out of Burma
and Bangladesh and parts of India
Manipur and mizoram so that is underway
and that affects India it also affects
China badly and this upcoming US
military base St Martin's island is
going to be you know it's going to
enable the Americans to project power
like never before in the Bay of Bengal
region and that also affects the malaka
strait which is kind of China's ailles
Hill so let's go to the map let's open
the map I'm glad we have occasion to see
the map right away so if you look at the
map M this island that the Americans are
going to acquire okay this tiny Island
over here St Martin's Island which is
ideally taped for creating a air base
and other things as well so from here
the Americans can possibly uh interdict
the straight of malaka now it looks like
a very tiny Island but the Americans
have very powerful power projection
capabilities very powerful missile
systems Etc they can definitely
interdict Chinese access to the state of
malaka which is disaster for China Burma
if it slips out of China's hand like it
already has it's a disaster for China
and the Chinese have various projects
that they would like to undertake in
Burma and now all of that comes within
range of St Martin's Island this future
upcoming US military base so overall
it's very bad for China and and let's go
back to the map and China is essentially
being encircled just like India is being
encircled by us proxies India is being
encircled by us proxies Nepal is kind of
a Chinese proxy and so Maldives but uh
when it comes to China Myanmar becomes a
US proxy Thailand all these Southeast
Asian Nations have very good relations
let's say with Thailand so does
Indonesia Malaysia so does the
Philippines right uh Japan South Korea
are are under us occupation so China is
being encircled okay they have Russia
that that they have reasonably good
relations with and they have a terrible
relationship with India which is
entirely China's fault India did not
cause this relationship to go so bad so
now maybe the Chinese are their
calculations are changing and maybe they
they are beginning to see that they need
to have better relations with India and
you can see the signs and symptoms of
that in the kind of uh official
government articles that are coming out
in uh the global times Etc which is a
Chinese Communist Party propaganda
mouthpiece media Outlet you can see
rather positive uh articles towards
India coming out which is very unusual
for the global times they have very
strident harsh towards India usually
that's happening uh one hears that the
government of India is now considering
allowing Chinese companies to invest in
India in joint V Ventures Etc well
that's an eye opener right and now
apparently like I'm I'm not I cannot
confirm this news I've not seen it
myself but assuming it's true well
that's another that the Chinese have
extradited a couple of individuals
that's interesting as well so it looks
like something is brewing but in I'm
saying this to Indian audience I'm sure
there are other there's a much wider
audience as well but to my Indian Indian
audience I'll tell you this that it is
very uh one has to be very careful when
it comes to trusting China okay I think
we have we should heed the lessons of
History the
Chinese they they uh are are a dangerous
customer to deal with one has to be very
careful with them you cannot assume that
because they say a few nice things they
become friends with India all right uh
their past track record from the 1950s
until until let's say last week has been
rather dubious and very strongly anti-
India they used to support in terms of
arms ammunition funding logistical
support moral support diplomatic support
Etc various anti-india terrorist
elements separatist elements Insurgent
Insurgent elements in India's Far East
in India's what you call the Northeast
Etc they've done all that they in the
past have written articles about the
need to balkanize India the Chinese have
written that so one has to be very
careful when dealing with the Chinese
you can't suddenly believe that yeah we
can trust the Chinese
now you can trust but verify and the
trust will happen on in very incremental
Quantum steps quantized steps
essentially and for India to for China
to genuinely gain some amount of trust
Vis A India they will need to sit down
once and for all at the negotiating
table and demarcate the border with
India they have refused to demarcate the
border for decades they been dragging
their feet forever because they want to
keep that border dispute open so as to
keep on pressurizing India via border
incursions and whatnot so that would be
the first step we would need for us
being able to potentially think start
thinking of trusting China to a certain
extent okay one has to be very care
careful with China but overall that is
the
situation Rakesh Pandit says is the Giza
Pyramid or pyramids was it is it any
kind of electric device electric device
well I have seen no evidence of that
I you know when I was doing my master's
degree in physics there was this
professor he specialized in in
electronics that physics department I
was in was full of people who
specialized in electronics and this
gentleman this professor he was doing
experiments with pyramids you know like
small scale pyramids a kind of pyramid
you know two square meters or something
thing it's base and he was doing various
experiments it's interesting that people
actually have the desire to do
experiments in India so he was putting
various chemical Solutions inside the
pyramid at a certain part of the pyramid
and seeing what is the rate at which the
chemical reaction is progressing does it
if you put it inside inside a
pyramidical structure pyramidal
structure does it accelerate the
chemical reaction in some way beyond
what you would natur expect it to
progress like naturally all that so it
was interesting to do that I found it at
the time kind of pseudoscientific right
now I would say that why not if you have
a hunch that something may there may be
something somewhere then test it out so
he was doing proper scientific
experiments I'm not sure what the
outcome was but interesting so there's
always been this belief for a very long
time Among Us humans that pyramids are
special kind of structure if you look at
Indian temples Hindu temples for the
past 2 3,000 years you will see that
they are all all kind of pyramid shaped
they actually seek to replicate the the
pyramidal structure of Mount Kash okay
so there is some kind of fascination
with the pyramidal shape that that
geometric shape but as far as I know
there is no evidence that there is
anything uh
uh any any we don't quite know what the
purpose of the pyramids was right the
the Egyptian pyramids in Giza so let's
go to the map once again let's try and
find out where this pyramids are oh
where are am I going Egypt Miss so you
go to alqa Ciro and in the in the
outskirts of KIRO you have the pyramids
will I be able to discover them right
away or will it take me some
time okay where are the pyramids
PID of
Giza is right here there we have it okay
so these pyramids on the outskirts of
Cairo and if you look at the alignment
that's the belt of Orion essentially
so we don't quite know what the purpose
of these structures was you know uh in
Hollywood movies it is depicted as tombs
of pharaohs but I promise you that they
have not discovered a single mummy
inside a pyramid thus far so we don't
quite know what the purpose of these
pyramids was and there are hidden
chambers that that have been discovered
but not exploded yet and so on so we
there's a there's definitely a mystery
about what the purpose of the pyramids
was but as far as I know we have not
discovered any uh electrical device kind
of
purpose of the pyramids not as far as I
know so that is the answer I can give
you the answer is that there's a lot
about the world that we don't quite know
and this is kind of a mystery right now
all
right
okay
um Rahul Sharma says okay once again
Ukraine about Mr modi's visit to Ukraine
I think Mr Modi wants to make an
agreement of peace between Russia and
Ukraine to divert in US attention from
India smart move no look there's no no
agreement that's going to happen between
Russia and Ukraine the Ukraine war like
I said is a proxy war and it's a proxy
war between Russia and NATO Russia and
the US Ukraine is a puppet Ukraine is a
proxy any negotiations if they happen
will not be with between Mr zalinsky and
Mr Putin Mr zinski will be brought in as
as as a figurehead but the real
negotiating will will be between the
Russians and the Americans okay so if
any agreement of peace or whatever
happens it's going to be between Russia
and the US Russia and NATO not Russia
Ukraine Ukraine
unfortunately doesn't matter in this
conflict Ukraine is Canon F Ukraine is a
proxy so uh this visit is a curtsy visit
it it's it seeks to signal to the west
and to the east which is Russia that
India can mediate in this matter India
is uniquely positioned to have a good
amount of comfort and trust with both
sides so we are in a good position to do
that if they if both sides want that's
what it is and this does nothing to
divert us attention from India
whatsoever the Americans they they have
3,000 eyes they don't have two eyes okay
they have eyes and ears everywhere no
attention is being diverted from
everywhere everywhere anywhere
especially India the Americans are
definitely very much focused on the
subcontinent region right now see what
they did in Bangladesh right regime
change operation and there's more they
have lots of other proxies Pakistan is a
very valuable us proxy the Taliban
allegedly receives a weekly stipend of
what between 50 to 80 million in cash
from the Americans so once again that's
a proxy and so on so the Americans have
the tremendous amount of focus on the
Indian subcontinent region there's no
diverting their attention from
here all
right pritam Sharma says are Wars and
interference globally hurting the us
just like the British Empire is it too
much to handle for the Americans going
forward or is this the HG money they
Aspire for these wars are not hurting
the US yeah it kind of uh affects the
economy for sure it has definitely
depressed the European
economy uh Germany is not doing well at
all there are the other nations in
Europe are not doing well the economies
are depressed some are in recession Etc
so it it does affect the economy but the
Americans are fine with that they can
print dollars as they wish and they'll
be fine and look the British Empire
fought so many wars all all across
Eurasia Etc it did not affect them made
them stronger as long as they won the
wars and it served their interest the
Crimean War and so many other Wars so U
it's not going to be too much to handle
for the Americans like I said there have
a thousand eyes Thousand Years thousand
hands and feet and whatnot more than 800
extra territorial military bases and
much more so it's not going to affect
them at all they can certainly handle
that they are the world's most powerful
military Machine by far the only the
advantage the only Advantage the
Russians have over the Americans is
their nuclear warheads so yeah so the
Americans aspire to be to for the world
to be bipolar or uni unipolar place
unipolarity means they are the only
superpower they are the only superpower
but they don't unipolarity means there
are no other powers that can challenge
the us right now Russia can challenge
the US even the Chinese can kind of
economically to a some extent China
Challenge the US not militarily so right
now the US is not in a unipolar world
it's kind of a multi-polar world right
now the Americans either want a unipolar
world or a bipolar World in which you
have the US and China as the major
Powers they don't want Russia to be a
major power they are okay with China
being a major power because they can
handle China they know how to handle
China economically China is is an
economic power not much of a military
power whatever experts say China is not
much of a military power especially when
you compare China's military might with
the American Military might there's no
comparison whatsoever so that's the
situation
uh okay venkadesh coloni asks about well
physics please explain coriolis force
and how it affects Cyclones in different
hemispheres the corus force is a
fictitious Force it's a pseo force well
if you you've done some Physics you'll
get what it means see it it arises
because of the rotation of the earth
along its a around its axis right we
know that the Earth the planet
let me put this map again and let's do
some Physics with the map we know that
the planet is slightly tilted and it
rotates it rotates along the its axis
and the equator is is
where well the plane of rotation
essentially and this rotation of the
earth produces what we call the Coriolis
force and it uh essentially uh affects
the way in which these Cyclones are
formed so you will see clockwise and
counterclockwise Cyclones okay whether
you are depending on which side of the
Equator uron and that there is an
element of the Coriolis force in that so
the
essentially technically in terms of
physics you would call it a pseudo force
or a fictitious force and it is
something that definitely affects the
formation and the evolution of cyclones
hurricanes whatever you want to call
them typhoons on both sides of the
Equator
okay um
okay u u says does India possess possess
significant geopolitical dominance
globally despite struggling to handle
pressure from smaller countries like
Qatar in the past okay geopolitical
dominance so you say so once again let's
take a look at where India is located
let's remove the Pyramids of Giza we
don't need them anymore for now this is
where India is located
geographically right now India is the
largest power in the Indian Ocean region
and in the Indian subcontinent region it
is the second most powerful nation in
Asia and the third most powerful nation
in Eurasia after Russia China and then
you have India across Eurasia but the
actual most powerful nation in Eurasia
is the us because they have a
significant foothold and footprint
across Eurasia and they are by far the
most powerful Nation now if you talk
about the Indian subcontinent look at
the kind of Nations India is finds
itself surrounded with
Pakistan which is a US proxy Afghanistan
which has good relations with India
Taliban but it still is a US
proxy uh you have Nepal which
unfortunately of late has kind of become
a quasi Chinese proxy you have Bhutan
which is an Indian protectorate then you
have Bangladesh which is now a newly
minted us puppet state Sri Lanka you
could say it's a US proxy the Maldives
are a Chinese proxy the Maldives were
here we are
then you have Burma which is a in in the
middle of a terrible Civil War it is
torn torn in the middle of a civil war
less than half the country is in the
control of the government of Burma and
the rebels who control more than 50% of
the land are pro us Rebels they are us
funded
Rebels and then north of India you have
Chinese occupied debate and China which
is an anti-india region so overall India
finds itself surrounded by enemies now
are we able to prevent regime change in
Bangladesh we are not
right the Americans could do it right in
our backyard so do you does this look
like dominance to you I'm not saying
that India is is a is a weak power or
anything but everywhere in the world
there's a massive us footprint and that
is something India has to Simply accept
as a fact if the US footprint was not
there in the Indian Ocean region in the
Indian subcontinent region it would be a
whole different balance of power so
India is what you could say a middle
power a regional power a potential
future great power and don't even think
about the term superpower okay don't
even think about it this is just reality
this is just hard facts facts don't care
about anyone's feelings I am
as strongly pro-india as anybody you can
ever find anywhere in the world but this
is just a fact you have to be realistic
if you want the nation to go in the
right direction so that's where we are
we are not able to project proper
geopolitical power projection in our own
neighborhood south of south of the uh
south of India's Sea Coast you have the
American possession which is the British
Indian Ocean territory Theo Garcia from
which they can project power anywhere in
the region so India is essentially
surrounded by proxies of other nations
mainly American
proxies and India will have to grow to a
10 to 15 trillion trillion dollar econom
om my Mark if it wants to genuinely
start projecting power in the region and
affecting what happens in in other
countries especially uh affecting the
long-term fortunes and fates of other
countries in the region right now we are
not in a position to do that so there's
not dominance but the only good thing
for India which really works for India
is that we are fully
Sovereign and no other country in the
region is fully Sovereign Tibet is not
sovereign you think Bangladesh is
Sovereign they puppet government now a
pro us puppet government you think
Pakistan is a Sovereign Nation they are
a US proxy Afghanistan they they depend
on the US support you know the Taliban
receives a stipend allegedly from the
Americans weekly stipend and Maldives
well maldiv is kind of riding a strange
boat right now but yeah it's Chinese
proxy so India is the only Sovereign
Nation fully Sovereign Nation in this
region apart from
China and China is way more powerful
than India so where's the power
projection right now we don't have much
power projection all right India needs
to grow please understand where India
stands right now India has all the
potential to you need for India to
become for us to become a major power in
the next 20 years major as in what China
is today India can become in the next 20
years by 2050 India could even possibly
surpass China possibly the probability
is less by 2050 but very significant by
2070 but India if things go well will
definitely surpass China and become the
second largest economy in the world and
with that comes your military muscle
right with with economic muscle comes
military muscle so the potential is
there but there's also the potential for
lots of things to go wrong so we need
the right kind of leadership at the helm
in New Delhi or wherever the capital
will be in the
future and we need good luck as well and
good policies good economic policies
good foreign policy and much more so
that's the
situation mcloven says do you think
India is responsible for the flood in
Bangladesh and smiley right yeah so it's
funny it's a stupid claim that uh see
that's what I mean by Bangladesh has
become a US puppet a US proxy this is
the kind of
nonsensical uh narrative that's
emanating from Bangladesh right now that
media is putting it out and that that
population is eager to jump on this this
bandwagon so all lots of Bangladeshi are
saying on social media that India is
somehow responsible for floods in
Bangladesh
nonsense absurd it's an absurd
claim
okay uh pritam Sharma says when bases
and interference globally help the us
then why does Trump and other
Republicans
oppose us interference Trump even wanted
his army out of South Korea is it just
domestic politics look Trump can say
whatever he wants the
American Military machine will not allow
such a thing to happen Okay uh uh
obviously war is bad Etc and Trump has
been anti-war and Trump has a track
record of not starting a single War the
only President you can think of in in
the past I don't know how many decades
who did not start a single War so Trump
actually does put his money where his
mouth is but overall US foreign policy
doesn't change no matter who is in power
is the president who in office is the
president and Trump wanted to do a lot
of stuff which he was not allowed to do
so um it does obviously help the US it
it helps them maintain their Global
hegemony over everything or or resources
or Supply chains over Nations and so on
so uh when it comes to Trump he may
perhaps genuinely desire some kind of
more peaceful peaceful approach but it
it it's impractical and it it won't be
allowed to happen he if let's say
hypothetically Trump comes to power once
again in uh he wins the election the
upcoming election at the end of this
year he comes back to Power next
year if that happens and if he genuinely
wants the US Army out of South Korea I
don't think he's going to be allowed to
do that no matter what happens so it's
impractical and it's it's not going to
happen
Okay
uh nikil Shaw says Capital change in the
future
yeah India right you mean look it would
be good to have a different capital in
India we've had see we in India those
who are alive today we only think of New
Delhi is the capital and if somebody
proposes that you should change the
capital the standard reaction is an
emotional knee-jerk reaction how dare
you say such a thing how can you think
of different Capital City why
not in the past we have had so many
other
capitals of India in the past two ,000
years one of the well longest serving
capitals of of bat of India was
patliputra right it it's currently
called Patna historically patliputra
this was the capital of the morian
Empire the capital of Chandra Gupta
Moria the capital of Ashok
Moria it was the capital of the shunga
Empire it was the capital of the Gupta
Empire for quite some time right so we
had patliputra Patna uh We've had uin as
capital at various points in
time uh the capital has
also uh join we've also had purpur as
the capital at certain times currently
PESA so we've had many
capitals and today if you see the the
geographical location of New Delhi it is
let's let's calculate the distance
measure the distance very fast
it is about 350 kilometers from the
border with Chinese occupied Tibet and
it very much comes within range of
Chinese uh long-distance assets whether
it's missiles cruise missiles ballistic
missiles aircraft strikes the S400 which
we also have Etc so it's it's not good
to have your Capital so close to the
border with a hostile territory a
territory under hostile occupation
ideally you would want a capital that's
somewh situated somewhere in the middle
of the country I mean for example if you
look at tur okay historically
historically the capital for for for the
longest time was Constantinople
currently it's called Istanbul but
Mustafa kimal atat was kind of smart
that he made anara in the middle of
Anatolia as a capital it's got It's got
a very harsh climate very dry climate
very hot in the Summers very cold in the
winters but he made that the capital
made sense so I would say that India
also should have a capital somewhere in
the middle of the country somewhere
maybe in madhya
Pradesh uan could be a candidate or you
could create a new capital city uh
somewhere in the middle of the country I
think it makes sense that way and if you
look at the history of Delhi I mean some
people may say it's superstitious but
it's got a very bad history the past
Thousand Years terrible things have
happened there and Kings who have ruled
for there from there have have faced
lots of defeats and and even if you go
back to the Mahabharat era it is Indra
Pras right and so on K
Pras so I think it makes sense to have a
new
capital and it would be good if that
happens well I don't know if it'll it'll
happen anytime in the near
future because we don't like change
right uh stepen Dominic says what's
outside our universe is it another
universe or Multiverse or are we living
in a Quantum Universe just like Ant-Man
and wasp wasp Quantum Mania movie Inside
any other universe so I haven't seen the
Antman movie I'm aware of it that guy
becomes very small and goes to
apparently the quantum realm which is
unphysical but nice to have a movie like
that so the question is what's outside
of our universe well we don't know
that's a simple answer we have no means
of gathering data from Beyond the
observable universe the universe we
don't even know how large it is our
universe we know the observable universe
the one that we can observe the limits
of our observation the observable
universe has a radius radius of about 45
billion light years in a diameter of
twice that which is about 90 95 roughly
billion light years that's how big the
observable universe is that's the limit
of our observational Ability Beyond that
we don't we can't we can't see what's
there so we can't even we can't even
observe the entirety of the universe we
inhabit so when you have that situation
how will we know what's outside the
universe if there is anything at all so
we don't know of course there are lots
of theories of what could be out there
but those theories can neither be proven
nor
disproven they are neither provable nor
falsifiable theories and that is the
definition of an unscientific Theory I
mean it's mathematical you can
definitely do the math but you can't
neither prove or nor disprove it so you
have the string theory Multiverse you
have the maners interpretation of
quantum mechanics which says that we
could be inhabiting a Multiverse our
universe could be just one
of God knows how many other universes 10
raised to 500 potentially if you look at
the string theory landscape Etc so the
short answer is we don't know what's out
there whether there is another Universe
there are other universes out there
whether our universe is
simply a small ball inside a larger
universe or whether we inhabit the
interior of a black hole we don't know
the black hole idea can be dis one
because if you look at black hole
physics then how do you explain the
cosmic microwave background radiation
how do you explain Dark Energy how do
you explain the accelerating expansion
of the universe so that doesn't quite
fit but overall the answer in brief is
that we don't know what's out there and
that's what drives physics it's makes
it's what makes physics theoretical
physics cosmology astrophysics so
fascinating because there are so many
unanswered questions out
there all right um
dungar Singh Chan asks a very pertinent
question what does the US get by doing
the Strategic demographic change in
Europe and that to against their own
people what purpose could it possibly
serve well one would have to delve in
the realm of speculation to answer this
question see what you can look at as a
potential answer to this question what
you can look at is what is happening
and what is going to be the effect of
what's happening so right now what we
are seeing in Europe in the Western
European region is that there is this
large scale illegal immigration of
certain kinds of people into these
countries and the these EU this this is
happening in the EU European Union
Nations Nations and this open doors
policy immigration policy is being
driven from Brussels which is the
capital of the European Union it's where
the Europe Union headquarters is located
so the European Union is forcing these
nations to accept these refugees
so-called refugees now what does do
these refugees look like they are mostly
young men military age men and they
typically come alone alone they don't
come with family there are very few
women and children generally when you
have refugees coming in it's usually
going to be mostly women and children
and some men but here it's the opposite
way around it's just young men mostly
young men military age men
so it it's not really uh immigration or
or refugees coming in it's it's
essentially an invasion that's being
engineered now these individuals who
coming in are mainly from West Asia
Middle East some from Afghanistan Etc
and lots of people from certain parts of
Africa all young men and they have being
encouraged they been they have been
settled in various parts of Europe and
they being they are being given State
support in of various kinds and they
being encouraged to
integrate so to say into European
Society they're not integrating they're
imposing their culture essentially
that's why we have so many riots and
whatnot that are happening all over the
place and terrorist attacks and and so
on so what is that is the situation so
right now the local population the local
people in these countries are feeling
cowed down they're feeling intimidated
they're feeling helpless and powerless
and they're trying to fight back through
riots and whatnot but then the state
Machinery the police Machinery targets
the locals the the the natives the
indigenous people not The Outsiders The
Outsiders are allowed to do whatever
they want that's what you seeing
typically in Europe
so it's sending a message to the
indigenous Europeans that that you are
not in power and this is what's going to
be done to you and what will happen is
that these uh immigrants let's say
will intermar hope let's say with the
local women and over the next few
Generations a new European race will
emerge which is neither black nor white
nor whatever but not white
anymore so that's what's happening now
what does this do to Europe so first of
all that white supremacy disappears
because they're no longer white
eventually by 2100 let's say there are
very few white people left Europe
they're all mixed race so white
Supremacy no longer exists secondly this
the German ideal of this super super
race or or Superior race Uber mench that
dies a natural death if all Germans
become multi-racial so it essentially
destroys Europe it destroys Europe's
identity and that is that seems to be
the objective now what purpose does it
serve I mean the Americans the well the
EU is by the US and and similar things
are happening in the in in the US as
well the southern Border in the US is
open Mex from Mexico and tremendous
amounts of immigrants are being brought
in illegal immigrants and they are being
settled they are being transported by
the government of various parts of the
US and they're being settled in various
cities in various places the US is also
experiencing this thing and so what what
is the overall objective of this I'm not
really sure what the objective is apart
from completely destroying the white
race
uh and why would they want to do it well
beats me I I I don't know but what it
will do in Europe is that it will it
will destroy Europe's identity it will
destroy Europe's potential to be a great
threat to the us in the
future okay the the if you look at past
history the Monroe Doctrine emerged in
the US as a response to the perceived
threat from Europe at that time all the
power all the nations in in the Americas
were essentially European colonies the
Americans had gained independence from
from British the other nations and and
regions in in in South and North America
where European colonies and the
Americans felt a genuine threat from
Europe the Europeans were still very
powerful so the Monro Doctrine was a
response to that
eventually the Americans became very
powerful and then they won the second
world war and then they became the major
in in Europe I think they still have
nightmares of those German marching
boots and those Hugo Boss uniforms and
they want to end the threat once and for
all so I think that could be one
possible reason why they are doing
this all
right
um Anish says subnational diplomacy by
the US is in full force in India assume
or should we expect something big in the
coming months look look the Americans
are are Past Masters at subnational
diplomacy that's what happened in
Bangladesh by the way uh in the in the
in the months and years in the runup to
the regime change operation that that
they pulled off successfully so they
will engage with various political
parties that are opposed to the ruling
party uh they will cultivate certain
politicians that's what they've done in
Bangladesh they will cultivate the
opposition parties they will uh they
will have various assets in various
institutions in the education system in
the media Etc and they
will exploit and exacerbate whatever
divisions exist in the nation and they
will seek to create more
divisions and then they will seek to
destabilize the nation by by unleashing
protests typically student protests and
other protests by creating riots in like
situations Etc that's the standard
Playbook of regime change now regime
change in India is very difficult
because India is such a large Nation a
genuine vibrant democracy but uh you
what you can see is that the current
government is already not a majority
government it's a coalition government
so that gives them that gives outside
forces an opening so I think in the in
the months and years to come there's
going to be more such activity in India
more
protests more subnational diplomacy more
more attempts to destabilize the nation
more attempts to dislodge the government
from power they may pressurize various
members of the Coalition uh the NDA
coalition to withdraw support from from
the coalition government Etc so these
things will intensify it's going to be a
tough ride ahead for India but we need
to be prepared for
it
okay himon MAA says I've sent you an
email please check okay I'll check it
out I get so many emails every day it's
very
easy for me to miss emails but I'll see
I'll
see okay shubam Raj says contrary to
Abhijit chaa saying in runways podcast
Dr somat said ISRO is not leing behind
in terms of budgets throw some light on
it okay so I I saw that little segment
okay so what Dr snat said is that the
projects that are ongoing in ISRO are
well funded the project that are ongoing
in ISRO are well funded and sometimes
you may even have to return the unused
budget at the end of the year to the
government that is for the projects that
are ongoing my point is this do we have
any project in ISRO for creating
reusable Rockets rockets that land
booster rockets that can land
autonomously do we have a project for
that do we have a project for a Saturn
five class rocket in in ESO do we have
projects like those and we
don't now if you need if you were to
start projects like those if you were to
for example accelerate the chandran
program and have chandrian 10 send
humans to the Moon by
2035 and you will lead a much larger
budget but those projects don't exist
and those projects should exist if India
is to be a space Power which India needs
to be we cannot afford to lag behind and
be left behind in the Space Race the
Nations that will lead the world in the
in the space race in the 21st century
are the Nations that are going to rule
the world geopolitically India cannot
afford to be left behind right now there
are no Cutting Edge projects ongoing in
ISRO it is incremental progress that we
are seeing why after all these years
does ISRO not have a project for
reusable rocket technology we don't have
that this this chundra program is going
at a snail
space it's happening everything is
happening but it's happening very slowly
with small budgets so the projects that
have been greenlighted by the government
they have adequate budgets small budgets
and it is sufficiently budgeted for my
point is there is there is a lack of
ambition not within ISRO but outside of
his in green lighting ambitious projects
that's the point we should have
ambitious project projects which which
will require a lot of money and those
projects don't exist that's why the
budget doesn't
exist that is the point so Dr snat is
right that whatever projects exist they
are well funded but those are small
projects compared to what's happening
outside India compared to that these are
small projects that we working on we
have a mongan mission coming up sometime
soon the next andrean mission will be an
incrementally better one in a few years
we have something coming up to Venus
shukan these are small little
incremental changes we need to have a
proper integrated plan an ambitious plan
of in of let's say an Indian moon base
with human beings on it by 2040 the
first chandran human the first Indian
moon landing with human beings should
happen by
2035 we should have an accelerated time
frame and we should have and and the
moon mission the human moon mission of
India should be let's say chandrian 10
so we need to have seven more Chandra or
or six more ch before that do we have
the budget for that we don't so that's
my point we need to be more ambitious
the government needs to be more
ambitious the government needs to start
more projects more ambitious projects
and for that you will need funding and
which is not there that is my point
that's my
point
okay Atul espart says Russia is immune
to American sanctions can you explain
why how did they achieve it and and does
does does the same apply to Iran and
China as well so what does this what
does it
mean to for the US to impose sanctions
on a
nation let's understand how it works the
Americans control most of the world's
economy firstly because their currency
the US dollar is the world's Reserve
currency you travel to any
country travel in the Indian
neighborhood somewhere nearby UAE um
Thailand Vietnam wherever it's okay to
carry US Dollars they'll be accepted
almost
everywhere mostly in in most big
establishments you carry Indian rupees
want work you will have to either carry
the local currency or US dollars but the
US dollar works everywhere it's the
global Reserve currency so the Americans
own the world's Reserve currency first
of all and secondly they own every
single essentially every single supply
chain they own that they control most of
the supply chains they control most of
the Nations that are the nodes of the
supply
chains and they control the Global
Financial system the Swift system
through which money is transferred
almost immediately anywhere in the world
and so on they control the entire
economic Financial framework of the
world now if they want to punish a
nation they simply cut that Nation off
from the framework so the supply chains
no longer work nothing comes in if the
nation wants to make a payment to
purchase something it can no longer use
Swift
and other nations will refuse to take
money from the nation because they're
scared of the US so Nation gets isolated
they can no longer trade with others
they can no longer import what they need
or export what they're manufacturing
that's how you get cut off from the rest
of the world and that's what devastates
nations by being cut off from the global
economy it devastates see what's
happened to Iran and you can do much
more you can deny uh supplies to to a
nation like like Iran for like the like
Obama did for for example you know
medical supplies and know whatnot
because of which you have tremendous
humanitarian crisis that can happen um
so that's what happens when you are
under sanctions India was under us
sanctions after the 1998 nuclear tests
for quite a few years ISRO was
sanctioned ISRO the they they even arm
Twisted the Russians into not selling uh
cryogenic rocket uh engine technology to
India we had to develop it on our own
which was actually good in the long run
so that is what happens when the
Americans sanction you they can sanction
certain companies they can sanction
certain individuals they can sanction
the whole nation and in the case of
Russia they have imposed every possible
sanction on Russia so what happened why
is the Russian economy doing well
despite the sanctions Russia's econom is
doing well despite the sanctions Russia
is econom is growing faster I don't know
four 5% way faster than than the other
European nations the Europeans Nations
don't consider Russia to be a European
nation but that's a different story so
what happened well I'll tell you why
it's because Russia is anarchy now what
do I mean byari look check out see the
size of Russia of course this is the
merant projection or because of which
the nation looks much larger than it
actually is but it is still a vast
Nation I don't know 11 12 15 I don't
know how many time zones they have and
they probably have about 50% of the
entire world's natural resources so
anything that a nation needs the
Russians have it they have unlimited not
well it's not unlimited but they have as
much coal as they need they have as much
iron ore as they need they have all the
raw ingredients they need for
fertilizers they have everything they
need for every industry they are a
tremendously large exporter of petroleum
products oil gas all of that so they
have everything they need that a nation
would ever ask
for and they have ensure that they their
their oil export Etc keeps going on
India has helped them a lot by
by by so Russia is now India's number
one supplier of of oil of crude oil
India is refining that and selling it to
other nations who need that so India is
is playing its part in the global
economy so because of these reasons the
Russian economy has complet has not been
affected at all and the Russians they
they they pegged their their currency
the rubble to the gold standard
essentially not quite gold standard but
close to it which is why the rubal is is
still still doing reasonably well as
opposed to what could have happened and
so on so that's why the Russians have
been they are the only nation that is
actually immune to us sanctions because
of these reasons because of these
reasons and because there so many things
that the world needs the world needs
that the Americans buy rocket engines
from Russia the Americans still buy
rocket engines from Russia they're
trying to wean themselves off those
those Russian engines but the Americans
have been buying that even after the
Ukraine war Russian rocket engines the
Americans have tried to reverse engineer
those Russian rocket engines they have
failed to do that that's how good those
rocket engines are the Americans are
able to manufacture them in America
Russian engines under license but
they're not able to reverse engineer the
engines and when it comes to space
launches the Americans until recently we
still uh going to space using the soyu
Rockets from bonor in Kazakhstan
so
that's what Russia has to offer to the
world and it's it's in a way
indispensable to the world and that's
why Russia is immune to us sanctions
Iran won't work Iran has been devastated
by us sanctions
devastated uh China the Americans can't
really sanction China too much because
the American economy and the Chinese
economy are kind of bound at the hip
okay the two the two economies are so
much integrated that it's almost
impossible for the Americans to sanction
China meaningfully without hurting the
the American economy as well so what
they can do is they can impose The
Selective sanctions on on the Chinese
for example uh prohibiting the the uh
export of various kinds of chips to
China for example to to to arrest
China's AI growth Etc and so on so forth
so they can do things like that they can
impose trade and tariff barriers on
Chinese Imports Etc but overall sanction
China the way they' sanctioned the U the
Russians is not feasible for the
Americans all
right bandar bji says what are your
views on climate activists protesting by
spraying orange paint on Stonehenge and
other places these people are barbarians
these are historic sites these are
Global Heritage sites in my opinion I
know it's in it's in British Islands but
it's okay it's it's it's several
thousand years old it's it's a monument
that is the collective Heritage of all
humanity and by spraying orange paint
paint on Stone Edge and trying to to to
damage this incredibly ancient Monument
what do they hope to achieve these
people are barbarians they're
idiots and these people are hypocrites
these climate change activists Etc they
will generally work for organizations
like like Green Peace Etc which are
hypocritical organizations I've known
that for a very long time even when I
was a student a student I was aware that
Green Peace is is the the people at
Green Green Peace are a bunch of liars
and cowards you know so I don't know
what they're trying to
achieve climate change is going to
happen whether you like it or not it's
happening and for us to arrest climate
change or to or to or to slow climate
change down all the nations in the world
will have to come together and reach to
and come to certain agreements which are
going to be very difficult to
implement so by going out there and
doing these by by performing these
Antics and virtue signaling is not going
to change the world or save the
environment it's it's I I suppose it's I
suspect it's just a bunch of attention
Seekers and narcissists who do this very
very
unfortunate
okay the lightbringer says thank you my
question is what are solar sales and are
they really that good for Interstellar
travel okay what are solar sales basic
physics lesson there is
something there is a concept in physics
it's a phenomenon which is called
radiation pressure so let's so in the
past or even today we have ships and
boats that travel under the power of
wind they have these sails that are made
of canvas or thick cloth and and those
are pushed by the various Trade Winds
which can be reasonably predictable and
that's how these ships sailing ships
Schooners Etc they traveled in the past
and they can still travel today that's
from because of the pressure that the
wind exerts on the sails that pushes The
Vessel forward in the sea the same
principle applies to radiation pressure
what is radiation radiation you can
think of it in terms of photons light
the sun is our primary source of energy
what energy is it it's radiation
radiation in the term in the form of
mainly photons there's obviously neutros
as well there's a solar wind as as well
as as plasma but let's talk about the
photons the solar wind the
solar radiation the light so this light
that comes from the sun if you have a
thin enough film with very small weight
then you will find that this radiation
which comes from the sun actually pushes
that sail forward in a direction
opposite to to where the radiation is
coming
from now you can take this phenomenon
and use it for space travel in the sense
that you can make a spacecraft which is
a tiny micro spacecraft with a computer
chip and all that and maybe a small
camera what whatever then you can put
that you can equip that with a very
large sale let's say a sale that is 100
square m in in area let's say
hypothetically okay you put that out in
Earth's orbit for example and then you
then you shine an array of lasers on
that light sail those lasers need to be
very powerful lasers but if you shine
sufficiently powerful lasers on the
light sail you can accelerate the light
sail to 20 or 30% the speed of light and
you can send it in a very specific
direction for example to Proxima centor
our nearest star system so if you were
to travel to Proxima centor using the
best chemical rockets that we have you
know it would take maybe I don't know
thousands of years tens of thousands of
years but if you
use I'm not sure if it's thousands of
years but it it will take a very long
time okay I don't remember exactly what
the calculation is I'll not do it in my
head right now but yeah it will take a
very long time but if you use light sale
technology and you accelerate the light
sale equipped spacecraft to 20 or 30% of
the speed of light you can reach there
in a few years maybe a decade or two
maybe two or three decades so that's
what light sale technology can offer
offer us we are almost there we almost
have the technological means to make
this happen there is a project called
project star starshot something I forget
the name but yeah uh it's definitely
feasible with the techn with the kind of
Technology we have right now the only
impediment right now is to have
sufficient ently powerful lasers and
that's simply a question of when not if
so maybe in 5 or 10 years we will have
those lasers those laser ared powerful
enough to accelerate a light sell to 20
30% the speed of light then we can we
can actually launch this breakthrough
star shot project so that's what solar
sales are and they can be really good
for inter Stellar travel now imagine you
make a light cell that
is that is 100 square kilometers then
very thin very thin light sail 100
square kilometers and you put a
spacecraft with let's say three people
in in that hypothetically okay just as
as an example then if you have
sufficiently powerful lasers which will
need to be very more powerful then you
can accelerate human beings to 20 30% of
the speed of light and send them to
Proxima centor in a matter of two or
three decades so that's what this
technology can can
offer okay
Anish Anish says you tweeted a few days
ago that
elagabalus kabalo was the best Roman
ruler ever or european ruler ever who
was he could you please tell us about
him well elagabalus was a shortlived
Roman Emperor he lived he ruled for a
brief short period of time four years
maybe maybe five years look it up look
it up okay Google it I don't remember
how long it was the rain but it was very
brief
R um he became emperor when he was a
teenager and his rule as the emperor
ended when his own petorian guards
assassinated him and his mother his
mother too I think was assassinated with
him now why
was so when I said he was the best
European R ruler ever I was being
sarcastic he probably was one of the
worst rulers of all time and he was a
very interesting individual he was
definitely of that persuasion what lgbtq
plus
persuasion and he
transformed the palace
into an lgbtq essentially amusement park
or something and uh obviously when you
have a ruler like that who is more
interested in these Pursuits personal
pleasure Pursuits of personal pleasure
and all that rather than ruling the
Empire then that ruler very quickly
loses the respect of the Armed Forces
ETA and then what happens
happens okay so I think he was he had
some ancestry from from Syria or
something that region the the West Asia
region and uh somehow he became the
emperor it's a very convoluted story but
his rule did not last long and
eventually he was assassinated by his
petorian guard that's in brief about
elagabalus so yeah the the world is
going back in that direction we are
perhaps in the age a new age of iLab
Balo
okay rhan Assan says you are talking
about widening your Siliguri Corridor by
occupying the territory of Bangladesh
but why why would you want to our
sovereignty for your country's safety
okay let's take a look at the
map uh the Siliguri Corridor so I'm
assuming rahan Anan is from rayan Assan
is from Bangladesh okay so this is the
Siliguri Corridor this small strip of
land between which
connects in the so-called Mainland India
with India's Far East you know the seven
states in the Far East of India and this
Corridor is approximately
24 kilometers wide okay so that's a
choke point and it's very dangerous for
India because a hostile Nation could
attempt to take it over and cut off
India's access to the Far Eastern region
of India now I have spoken about Ving
the S silur Corridor Siliguri Corridor
by acquiring some land from Bangladesh
hopefully in a very peaceful friendly
manner but obviously obviously I
understand why the people of Bangladesh
would be very unhappy with that I
understand your sentiments completely if
somebody told me that we're going to
take some part of your country for our
purposes obviously it will infuriate me
so I understand why the people of
Bangladesh feel this way now the
question is now the point is why would I
say this look understand this my
Bangladeshi friends Bangladesh is an
artificial Nation it has always
historically for thousands of years
being part of the Indian civilization
Bangladesh is nothing but one part of
the Bangladesh what is called Bengal
today Bangladesh is East Bengal Wang and
West Bengal is the state of West Bengal
and India today this region was
artificially our
nation was artificially partitioned by
foreign powers for their own
benefit okay and our wonderful leaders
agreed for to for this to
happen and uh in 1971 India reconquered
this land liberated East Pakistan we
should have actually absorbed this
territory into our our nation after a
brief period of just 24 years because
Bangladesh was always part of India now
the situation is that there are and you
know many parts of Bangladesh should not
have many parts of East Pakistan should
not even have been part of East Pakistan
because they have significant Hindu
majorities there now it's no longer the
case because the population demographics
have been totally re-engineered and very
few Hindus left in Bangladesh today 7%
or something of banglades population is
Hindu in 1971 it was 20% plus 22 23% in
1947 it must have been close to 30 40%
I'm not sure so you have significant
Hindu populations in the rangapur Raj
Shahi region you have significant
Buddhist Hindu population in chatram
region those could be reabsorbed into
India simply on the same on the basis of
the same argument which was the
religious
demographics and and obviously the other
situation I'm sure that rahan Anan will
not agree with me is that there is an
ongoing persecution of Hindus happening
in Bangladesh right now the media is not
reporting it they are trying to
essentially to essentially continue the
agenda of 1971 in 1971 the objective of
the Pakistani army was to destroy was to
eradicate Hindus entirely from from East
Pakistan so right now some of that is
happening once again and there are all
kinds of horrible things coming out on
social media about what's happening to
Hindus so I would argue that IND should
provide
help of material help financial
help arms ammunition whatever is
required to Bangladesh is Hindu the
Hindus of Bangladesh to create a
separate Bangladesh for themselves where
they can be safe and maybe we can absorb
some part of rangapur Raj Shai Etc to
widen the sori corridor for our national
interest look that's how the world
operates I have my interest you have
your interest I am more powerful I'm
going to do what's best for me the world
of geopolitics the only law the Only
Rule in geopolitics is the rule of the
Jungle might is Right unfortunately now
I I don't wish anything ill to the
people of Bangladesh you are anyway my
people we are the same race the same
ethnicity the the only thing that
separates you and makes you hate Makes
You Hate My People is religion that's
the only thing and I know there's a
tremendous amount of anti-india ha tr.
in Bangladesh the thing is look India
has to look out for its interests and
the subcon the subcontinent borders have
changed multiple times in the past 70 80
years and they will change again and how
will the change they will change B they
will change based on uh the interests of
the most powerful nations in the region
so my country safety is very important
for me I would in the long run would
like to see the subcontinent United
again like it has always been Bangladesh
the people of Bangladesh are descendants
of Indians you have the same language
you you're the Bengali language has more
Sanskrit than many other languages in in
Northern
India the only thing is that there is
this tremendous hat trade for India
right now so that's what I would have to
say look I I I have no ill will for the
people of Bangladesh I want the people
of Bangladesh to have as much Prosperity
as is humanly possible as much happiness
and peace as as is possible but this the
the borders will change that nothing can
stop that okay if if one thing you can
learn from history it is that borders
are never sacran borders always change
and borders change in a direction that
is outward from the more powerful Nation
that's how it works so there you have it
that's
all okay
okay saaria s says what do you think
about Poland geopolitics now that's an
interesting Nation Poland the
geopolitics of Poland so first of all my
friends let's find out where Poland is
on the map of the world because that's
not a nation that we often talk about in
the Indian subcontinent so here's where
we are this is the Indian subcontinent
you go westwards there's a temporary
Nation then there's Persia then there is
West Asia there is Turkey
you go north of turkey you have the
Black Sea north of Black Sea you have
Ukraine where the war is going on and
west of Ukraine you have
Poland now like I just said just a few
minutes just a minute ago the borders of
the world change and these were not
always the borders of Poland okay the
city of LV was part of Poland in the
past there was a time when there was no
Poland either you know Poland had been
divided up by the Germans and the
Russians the molotov ribbon trop pack
and so on but right now you have this
nation called Poland which is west of
Ukraine and west of
Belarus now you know if
you if you look at what western
commentators have to say they are
placing a lot of emphasis and a lot of
Hope on Poland when I'm when I say West
I mean NATO I mean Americans and West
Europe which is NATO those commentators
so look Ukraine is right now embroiled
engulfed in the conflict the Ukraine war
the special military operation and
eventually most probably the the outcome
is going to be that Ukraine will be
partitioned most likely Kiev will have a
neutral government and Ukraine will be
partitioned maybe along the nier or
maybe along some other line and it is
also possible that some parts of the
westernmost region of Ukraine may be
reabsorbed by Poland that is one second
Poland is probably very soon going to be
Europe's number one military power they
already have in Poland more tanks and
more artillery more howitzers Etc then
Germany already and they they have been
they are in the process of buying lots
and lots of weapons from the US and also
from South Korea maybe a thousand more
tanks and much more other stuff they're
going to get a whole bunch of F35
fighter planes from the Americans so
Poland is going to be the next European
military super power that's what the
Americans are transforming Poland
into okay now so so it could be the next
bulwar the next nation in line after
Ukraine now the West likes to say that
Russia is trying to recreate an Empire
and it's going to march westwards in
that case Poland is very important for
the West okay so that is the military
importance of Poland it's a rising
military power the what kind of
government do you have in Poland you had
a right-wing government that lost the
election recently and you have Mr Donal
tush I believe who is right now the
leader of Poland he is kind of a
moderate not too right not too left
somewhere in between but he is way more
positively predisposed to the US than
the previous
leader Poland is one of the one of the
hold out nations in Europe when it comes
to immigration Poland and Hungary are
paying a daily fine to the to the
European Union because they are not
allowing immigrants to come in you know
those wonderful immigrants military age
men uh so Poland right now is is in that
situation so that's what I have to say
about Poland in geopolitics it's an
important nation in Europe uh possible
next military superpower in Europe not
superpower but next major European
military power uh Germany is being de
industrial so maybe the Focus will now
be on
Poland and Mr Modi is going to visit
Poland in a day or so isn't he it's
going to be an interesting visit and
let's see what the outcomes are there's
a lot of history of late between India
and Poland when the Second World War was
happening when Poland was divided
between Germany and and the USSR it was
it was under occupation by two Nations
and you had lots of Polish refugees who
were trying to escape to other nations
and uh there was a ship full of Polish
women and children who were trying to
get Refuge somewhere but nobody was
giving them permission to Dock and to
and to come and and to offboard the ship
and uh the and that ship even came to
India okay that ship came to India in
the 19 I don't know early 1940s I I
assume and the British did not give
permission to the ship to dock in India
but the uh Maharaja of junad gave them
permission to come off to come ashore
and he gave those refugees those Pol
those polish refugees uh Refuge shelter
in his kingdom as long as the War lasted
he became their their Foster father
essentially and there was another
Maharaja I forget where somewhere in
Maharashtra who also did something
similar so India was very kind to Poland
even though India was at that time
itself under foreign occupation British
Pol occupation but the Maharaja of
junard was very kind he became a foster
father to those kids and to those people
who had come in and I think there is a
great deal of warmth because of the
story still towards India in Poland
there are there are Town squares named
after the Maharaja Etc so that's an
interesting bit of history between
recent history between India and Poland
Poland could become more important
geopolitically because of its military
rise and it could play an important role
going
forward in the days and years to come
VII Manar says do you ever consider
joining politics you are needed as a
policy maker look politics is a whole
different uh ball game uh I have never
ever considered joining politics I don't
think I ever will because it's a whole
different world and I'm not I'm not sure
I I'm pretty sure I'm not equipped for
that politics it's all about look
politics is the art of making
compromises and whatnot okay and uh
so I'm not sure it's it's for everybody
so I have never considered joining
politics I don't think I ever
will if somebody if the government would
want me as a policy maker or as adviser
I will obviously be happy to to offer uh
whatever I can but politics may not be
the right thing for
me okay arifin shua says can the world
ever become a single political entity in
the next Grand
Century well there could be look the
Americans would like a unipolar world
what does a unipolar world means it mean
it means it's a defacto world
government so right now for example let
me give you a taste of what could happen
if there is a single World Government
okay so right now you have a nation you
have these nations that are under us
occupation but the world sees them as as
independent Sovereign Nations Japan
South Korea okay their their economic
policy their foreign policy their
military policy is all controlled by the
US Japan as well as South Korea but the
world sees them as independent nations
So eventually what would happen is that
every country in that world in the world
could be controlled by just one
superpower and these nations all the
nations in the world could be
technically independent but their
economic foreign policy and and and and
military policy could be controlled by
the superpower in that case you could
have a world government by Pro without
the world even realizing there is a
single world government or you could
have an over world government in which
every nation's government is destroyed
and a single government officially takes
charge from somewhere maybe Washington
DC maybe maybe somewhere else could
happen um so if us hegemony continues to
to grow which it could which it very
well could because of AI and
technological advances then you could
have a defacto world government in the
next 20 30 years possibly maybe even
before that right uh so it's possible
and it could it's possible that you you
will have a world government and you
will not even realize it that's also
possible so POS the possibilities are
endless and a world government is not a
good thing let me assure you of
that especially a hidden covered World
Government
um Anish says I'm losing hope in this
country India after seeing Mr Modi
taking U-turn in every good decision
look imagine how worse things could be
if Mr Modi was not in
power okay I know it's a he's heading a
coalition government right now and there
are many more constraints on what he can
do but imagine the alternative to the
the the NDA government to Mr Mod's
government imagine that government is
not in power and the opposition is is in
power then you can lose hope in the
country then you can lose hope in the
country I think there is still hope okay
and I don't think Mr Modi is making
u-turns u-turns in every good decision
some some things you know
you we sitting here are not able to see
every threat that the nation faces there
are threats coming from outside the
country there are threats that are
positioned within the country as well
foreign assets and other assets of
various kinds that are embedded in the
country
and there are all kinds
of
parameters to
consider so sometimes you have to do the
the hard thing and and walk back
sometimes yeah the farm laws there were
good laws but Mr Modi decided to walk
back on that and so you can I'm sure
there are one or two more things you can
think
about uh the main thing is that uh the
long-term and large scale National
interest has to be always uh prioritized
and I'm pretty
sure I am seeing only that so I know
that after the results of the general
elections there's been overall downturn
in the mood of the
nation but I think we are still in good
hands and we have to make sure we elect
the right people in power okay you
cannot you cannot make decisions based
on
emotions so I would say that there is
still a tremendous amount of Hope for
the country India is still in good hands
India is still going in the right
direction Mr Modi is facing different
kind diff a different set of challenges
this time in his third term and I'm
pretty sure that he will make the right
choices the right decisions and he has
the strength and the fortitude and the
experience to steer India through the
troubled waters that we are going to be
experiencing more of in the coming years
so it is good that we have Mr Modi in
power there are lots of attempts to D
stabilize India and to to hamper India's
progress and to to to destabilize
India's neighborhood that are happening
right now and all these things put
together can make it look like the
government is kind of weaker right now
but the alternative is is is Unthinkable
so I'm glad Mr modi's power so I would
say overall be positive be optimistic
not everything is a U-turn many of the
policies are still continuing just the
way they were and I'm pretty sure many
good things will come up in the coming
years so do not lose hope you have to be
positive you have to be optimistic
what's the alternative being depressed
and being miserable come on come on
there's always hope and there is genuine
hope okay
so Viba says Modi visited Poland
yesterday okay okay okay I okay was it
yesterday I thought it was zinsky first
and then Poland it is the other way
around all right
cool um mcloven says do you think the
Modi brand is under decline
that's an interesting question look
Brands yeah Mr Modi is a brand you're
right a brand is a set of perceptions
and ideas Etc and uh every brand has a
rise and a decline at certain points in
time so uh Mr modi's thirdd term is in
progress right now the first term he he
got 273 seats in Parliament the second
term he got 303 three seats and this
time he's got 240 240 something seats
right in Parliament so there's been a
downturn now definitely you could say
that the brand could be somewhat in
Decline and given his age I don't see
him running for elections as as the
Prime Minister candidate in 2029 2029 I
don't think it would be advisable by the
time the BJP and the NDA would have
should uh put forth new leaders
and they have five years to discover the
right kind of leadership so I think that
uh brand could be somewhat in Decline uh
Mr Mii definitely uh doesn't have the
kind of powerful government he had the
last two times it's a slightly more uh
challenging time for him and most likely
this is going to be the the the
five-year period in which he probably
transitions uh the Reigns of power to a
new Prime ministerial candidate but it
is still a very important time for India
maybe the most important time for India
this next five years because the
challenges are going to
mount
okay
uh samat says you are live on Republic
TV I was live half an hour ago I I I was
live at 8:00 8:00 p.m. so there was a
discussion on Republic TV with Arab Arab
goobi about about the about prime
minister modi's visit to Ukraine so I
spoke spoke briefly in that so I was
live between 8:00 8:00 p.m. India time
and 8:30 p.m. India time I'm not sure if
they are rerunning that right now but
I'm live here right now and I'm
interacting with you guys in real
time
um VII Manar says how are the Israeli
people so patriotic and well equipped
what is special about their education
system could you please throw some light
on the education system of Israel okay
so I don't know a lot about the
education system of Israel I've not
studied it studied it in any depth what
I would what I can tell you first of all
the education is in their mother tongue
the Hebrew language in India people like
me had to be educated in the English
language today if you're a kid and you
want to have a good career a good job
you have to speak good English with a
proper accent you speak English with the
Indian accent you will not get a good
job not at all that's the problem you
see
so so there is this perception in India
that if you don't speak good English
you're not educated you're
illiterate and that creates this
tremendous sense of inferiority among
Indians there is no such thing in Israel
they are happy to speak Hebrew they
happy to speak broken Hebrew accented
English and that does not give them a
feeling of inferiority secondly I'm
pretty sure that the history they teach
in the Israeli education system is a
history that that puts Israel front and
center and it promotes a sense of pride
in being Israeli and
Jewish in India you get the opposite
thing they don't there is no open
blatant Hindu phobia probably in most of
the education system but overall the
attitude is that Indians Indian history
is is is a series of defeats and Indians
are an inferior people and the British
came did did India a favor by by
occupying India for two half centuries
and everything the British did was good
for India we did not have Railways
before the British came we did not have
education before the British came
without the English language there could
be no progress and so on so forth so the
education system systematically deines
and brainwashes the Indian kids and
turns them into self-loathing people
with a tremendously deep de rooted
inferiority complex and that's what it
does okay and it the Indian education
system also fails to instill a sense of
patriotism
and nationalism in the Indian people
that's the problem
right in I've seen in some textbooks
they they portray Pakistan occupied
Kashmir as aad Kashmir can you believe
it and the Indian academics especially
when it comes to the humanities many of
them are
compromised many of them are
compromised and these marxists and
leftists have a strangle hold in on the
IND Indian education system there is is
no such thing in Israel and obviously in
Israel there is a tremendous emphasis on
science and technology on engineering on
excellence and most importantly the
Israel education system prioritizes
Merit the Indian education system does
not prioritize Merit it's full of
reservations for all kinds of special
interest
groups that's the problem I could go on
and on about the Indian education system
but yeah that's what Israel is doing
right and what India is
not and if you if India does want to
become a great power in the future we
need a patriotic population we need a
population that is not burdened with a
crippling inferiority complex we need a
population that is proud of the local
culture the local civilization the local
languages and we need a population that
is proficient in science and
technology and the Indian education
system does none of these things
okay so if you want to know exactly
what's wrong with the system Indian
education system and what can be done to
change it uh watch ask Abit episodes I
don't know around 2930 around that
around that number there are three
episodes I believe in which I've spoken
about the education system and I've
given the root causes of everything
that's wrong specifically the things
that are wrong in the education system
and the things that need to be done to
change it I've given everything out in
detail
okay bookshelf to when yeah um thank you
for the
reminder I have a whole lot of books
that I need to show you I will do it
soon I will I
will T Chandra says I have been
following Dr mahang baluch and currently
the situation is very tense in
baluchistan people are being kidnapped
why isn't India taking action in the
United Nations is it due to Iran good
question you ask oh the last part
especially uh so I remember sometime in
2014 2015 2016 in during his first term
Prime Minister Modi during his address
from the Red Fort whether it was 26th
January 15th August I don't remember but
he had mentioned baluchistan once and
then there was it so uh the situation is
bad in baluchistan this lady Dr mahang
Balo she's a reasonably young lady she's
a medical doctor her father was was
disappeared by the Pakistani Army and he
was murdered I believe and his and her
brother was also kidnapped I believe for
a period of a few months and tortured
but surprisingly released and you have
these enforced disappearances these
these killings of of innocent civilians
that happens this this thing happens in
baluchistan on an ongoing basis it's
been happening for decades it's a reign
of terror by the Pakistani military in
the region baluchistan is being
exploited nothing is being given out
given back to baluchistan baluchistan is
is rich in natural resources oil gas all
that let's go to the map where is
baluchistan you ask me it's uh it's this
region look uh Karachi is the capital of
Sy and west of Sy you have baluchistan
so the Iranian city of zahedan it is
close to the bistan Border qua is in
baluchistan if I'm not mistaken yeah
beluchistan so it's a very large region
part of Pakistan it used to be historic
India's border with
Iran so it's it's rich in oil and gas
and you have this very important port of
gu over here which has been handed over
to to the to the
Chinese uh so the balistan region is
being exploited it is all the natural
resources are being extracted out of it
but nothing is being given back to the
people of baluchistan who are being
brutalized for a long time and this
Brave lady Dr mahang Balo has been
speaking out against that and I'm very
surprised that she is still a ble to do
that uh so that's the situation so why
isn't India doing any actions in the UN
is it due to Iran go back to the
map map here so understand
this the baluchistan that is in Pakistan
is roughly only half of the actual
region of baluchistan the other half is
in Persia it's in Iran so the port of
chabahar that India is involved in the
part of chabahar is also part of
baluchistan okay there are two major
ports in baluchistan guad and chabahar
this entire region of Iran the Western
the eastern most region of Iran is also
baluchistan it is Iranian baluchistan
the people are the same they speak the
baluchi
language now if India were to support
the aspirations the freedom aspirations
of the baloi people of Pakistan Pakistan
occupy bistan then the same aspirations
would
be well indirectly supported in the
Iranian part of baluchistan also so yeah
we have good relations with Iran we
don't want to spoil that it doesn't make
sense for us to do that so that's why we
are not not pursuing this matter very
vigorously right now so Iran is
definitely a factor in this and the
other factor is that Pakistan is a us
wasal Pakistan is a US Cent State proxy
State puppet state and we can't afford
to do too much in their right now for
the time being so for these
reasons for these reasons
okay an prash says did you watch beer
biceps new podcast with Dr with his Ro's
chairman Dr s I haven't seen it I saw a
few small Clips very good that ranir got
a chance to speak with Dr snat and I
will as soon as as I get the time I'll
I'll check it out so yeah we are all
obviously very proud of ISRO and and I'm
glad that rir has spoken with Dr snat
and
you know it will help
uh uh it will help the people of India
fall in love with space exploration
science technology all that if if this
sort of content is promoted so it's
wonderful that rir did this and I will
certainly check it out at the first
opportunity
okay okay M liven says Julian Assan is
free how did that happen did he make a
deal with the devil no Julian asalan was
powerless and I suppose the West was
looking very bad by keeping him uh
under under bars Behind Bars the
Americans were looking very bad okay so
I think they let him go and they've
imposed certain conditions on him that
he cannot say this or say that or
whatever and overall his wings have been
clipped he will not no longer be allowed
to do whatever he was doing with
Wikileaks Etc so they have essentially
turned him into a harmless person a
person who can't do too much and they've
allowed him to walk free with terms and
conditions attached there's no deal with
the devil there's no deal with the devil
of course he had to sign some legal
agreements and all that which says that
he cannot do this do that or say say
certain things and take certain actions
so kind of you could say deal with the
devil but it was enough right he had
been in prison for such a long time
terrible Freedom where's the freedom of
speech over here freedom of expression
freedom of speech doesn't apply to jul
nange right such is the
hypocrisy Banu Gopi says what's the
point of becoming a superpower if you
can't even protect brothers and sisters
in Bangladesh after vixit b47 there will
be no Hindus left who is saying that
India is a superpower what is the
definition of the word super
power from my perspective my definition
of the word superpower means it is a
nation it is a power that can intervene
militarily anywhere in the world at 60
minutes
notice anywhere on the globe look look
here's the globe you see this globe
let's spin it take any location on the
planet and a superpower as a nation that
can intervene militarily anywhere in the
planet at 60 minutes notice that is a
superpower and of course that Nation
will control the world's economy and the
world Supply chains and everything else
that's superpower is India a superpower
from the definition no India is not even
close to being a superpower so who's
saying India is a
superpower and you are right India is
currently not in the position to protect
our brothers and sisters in Bangladesh
so India is not a
superpower the point of becoming a great
power is that you can do it right now
India can't so India should aspire to be
a great power forget about being a super
power a great
power so that's what we have to work
towards we should not be cynical and
saying and say that what's the point of
being a superpower what's the point of
being Vish Guru I don't like the term
superpower I don't like the term visha
Guru I don't like the term vuda
kumaka India should Aspire India should
should work acidly work towards becoming
a great power and becoming the eminent
power in the Indian subcontinent region
with power protction capabilities in the
significant portion of the Indian Ocean
region then we will be able to protect
our brothers and sisters and our friends
and allies wherever we want in the
region that is the whole point of
becoming more powerful right now we are
not so we need to go in that direction
and vixit bat is a is is that if we
become a developed country by 2047 it
will mean that we will have a 10 15
trillion 20 trillion dollar economy
maybe 30 trillion economy if we have
that sort of economy imagine the
military power that we will have we will
be able to protect
people in that eventuality so that's
what we need to work towards we need to
be more
positive this defeatist attitude is not
going to serve us be more positive and
how do you be positive by working
working in that direction and not
spreading negativity please don't spread
negativity please don't spread a cynical
attitude I see so many people making fun
of the term visha Guru ET I don't like
the term but they use the term visha
Guru as a
cynical as as a means of making fun of
India and Indians use the term to make
fun of Prime Minister Modi and and India
overall by by using the word vishu
sarcastically see this is the situation
in Vish Guru see that's what happened in
Vish Guru visha Guru is going the right
track this negative sarcastic attitude
spreads negativity it spreads deism I
don't like this sort of behavior it
doesn't serve the nation it doesn't take
the nation in the right direction be
positive be optimistic and work as hard
as you can work towards what work
towards uplifting yourself work towards
developing yourself work towards
becoming more prosperous as an
individual
And if every individual does that we
will all rise together the whole nation
Rises together so you don't have to go
into Social Service to serve the nation
you don't have to join the government to
serve the nation just become
wealthy become as wealthy as possible
ethically and if everyone does that
imagine what how it will transform the
nation that's what needs to happen so
please be a little more positive all
right
um interesting question by rainbow were
all the dance and art forms introduced
to Europe by the
Ruma not all the dance and art forms but
some very important art and dance forms
were indeed introduced to Europe by the
Roma for example there is something
called
Flamingo right The National Music the
national dance of Spain flamingo guitar
is a very distinctive style of guitar
player
with its
own um scale right flamingo
scale and then you have flamingo dance
iconic flamingo dance so Flamingo music
and flamingo dance is Gitano is is Roma
in origin the Roma are Indian origin
people they were called by various names
the gypsies the Romani the Roma the
cinti the kalderash the C and whatnot
so the Roma people they introduced uh
they are the they are The Originators of
flamingo dance as well as music the
guitar playing Etc then there is a very
famous very very very important
uh form of music called gypsy
jazz and there have been very famous
very iconic uh musicians let me show you
some of these for example let's go to
Google okay
um now tell me what's the what's the
Hindi word for wake up what's the Hindi
word for wake up it's Jago right so look
at look at
this Jango
Reinhardt okay Belgian Jazz guitarist
and composer he was of Indian origin he
was Gypsy his name was not D Jango it
was Jago actually you can see he looks
quite Indian
so he he had an accident in his early
life and two of his fingers on the left
hand became dysfunctional as a result so
he used to play guitar incredible lead
guitar with just two fingers three
fingers including the thumb and he's one
of the one of the greatest Jazz
guitarists of all time so there is D
Jango Reinhardt there are so many other
U who know
winterstein this guy is another
guitarist he also he is a rhythm
guitarist in gypsy
jazz uh and there are so many other
people for
examp
Larin this guy is another Jazz guitarist
excellent uh guitarist one one of the
greats by now and I can I'm sure I can
think of many more what was
uh yeah that girl Shocking
Blue uh singer I forgot her name ah
Marishka veres he was of Indian origin
Gypsy her father was was a musician as
well and so on so the point is uh a lot
of the musical Heritage of Europe has
come from Indian origin gypsy people
there's a lot to unpack in there uh let
me also show you this if you want to
uh okay let's let's let's put Google
back over here and there was this movie
a very good movie
called okay it's by tonyi gatli tonyi
gatli is a French director who's of
gypsy who's of G Gypsy ethnicity and I'm
pretty sure this could be available
somewhere online
okay it is there on on YouTube I will
not play it here but it this movie if
you watch it it will trace the entire
entire historical Journey geographical
journey of the gypsies from India all
the way to Europe through a musical
journey and the various musical forms
that you have in Turkey gypsy music in
Turkey gypsy music in Egypt gypsy music
in Eastern Europe in Western Europe in
Spain and so on very good movie
Lum so so yeah if you are so inclined I
would encourage and invite you to watch
that
movie
okay
um RJ RK kington says how does mainland
India perceive the northeastern states
in terms of appearance cast and Creed to
what extent does the media portrayal and
divisive policies contribute to these
perceptions for the longest time the
longest time people in what we call Main
India had no idea that the Far East or
Northeast existed they have no idea of
it the education
system you would be forced to memorize
the the the the uh capital cities
itanagar infal kohima what dimapur agala
Etc and that's it so there is some part
of India which has these states and
these Capital Cities and that's it
nothing more than that and there was no
understanding of what kind of people
live there what kind of Customs they
follow nothing
whatsoever I'm talking about the 20th
century even the beginning decade of the
21st century there was absolutely no
connection between these desparate parts
of India okay so in what we call uh what
Mainland India people had no idea of
what the people in nagaland in Assam in
in Manipur in in tripura ET what these
people look like what kind of languages
they speak what is their way of life
what are their Customs like and so on
absolutely no idea and then when people
from these states eventually started
coming for work for Education Etc to
other states in
India the people of these states because
they have no understanding they probably
thought these people are Chinese or
something so there is because of this
lack of National integration there is
there there until recently has been a
very very distinctive lack of knowledge
understanding
Etc about the Far Eastern region of
India in what we call Mainland India and
there have been all these stereotypes
also that people create you know calling
everyone nepales something like that so
there are all these stupid stereotypes
also that have
uh cropped up Etc and I'm not sure what
the media Trail is I remember there was
a movie I forget the name of the
movie
um some Bollywood movie in the around
2010 or something maybe before that
amar's daughter had a brief role in the
movie in which the there was a story
about a b Bodo Insurgent or something so
the portrayal was very inaccurate very
wrong and very
stereotypical they were portrayed the
Bodo people were portrayed like Savages
essentially U then you have this movie
about Mary K in which Priyanka Chopra
portrays Mari
K does she look like a girl from the
Northeast from Manipur does Priyanka
Chopra look like that could they not
have
have have chosen selected an actress
from Manipur to play the role of marcom
but no they won't do it so media has
play played this role in in the rest of
India not understanding or having an
idea of what what the Far East is like
and so on so that's why there are all
these misperceptions misconceptions and
all but I think now that is becoming
lesser and lesser because people are
traveling more today India is
increasingly becoming more prosperous
people are traveling to various parts of
India it's easy to travel to any part of
India today if you want it it'll take
you a couple of hours to reach two three
hours to reach wherever you want and
people from these states in the Faris
are also coming to other parts of India
and mingling with the local population
settling down so now there is more
understanding but in the past it was
very bad it was very bad and yeah there
have been incidents of racism and all
that discrimination because of this lack
of understanding okay so yeah it's it's
it's it was a very very in the 1980s
1990s in the 20th century there was a
lot of blah blah blah lip service to the
idea of national integration there was
this news this this TV channel called
dur dasan the only channel the country
was allowed to watch in which every day
they would give speeches and lectures
slogans about National integration but
they did nothing about National
integration now the best way to
integrate a nation is by raising the
levels of prosperity and letting people
travel so that's happening now so I
think things will get much better in in
the coming years and things are much
better today compared to what it was
like in the 1980s 1990s even 2000s
things are much better today
um moit parashar says can India send a
man moon mission after gagan I think if
you look at the Timeline that's been
proposed India will send uh humans to
the Moon I think around
2040 now I have a video out on this
channel on this channel in which I've
said that we should send humans on the
Moon by 2035 and the the 2035 human moon
mission should be chandran 10 and what
what should chra and 4 5 6 7 8 9 be like
that also I've put out but uh that's not
going to happen it's going to progress
is going to be much slower so I think
earliest by 2040 we will have Indian men
or women or both on the moon
2040 or or beyond that uh gagan is the
human space space flight program of
India I think the first uh test launches
could happen this year or next year okay
unmanned mission to to validate the the
technology the the the capsule which
will carry the astronauts so you could
send a a dummy human being a robotic
human being and and sensors instruments
on board this uh test mission which will
monitor the the inside environment of
the capsule that it is it is safe or not
throughout the mission until splash down
so there could be one or two test
missions without human beings of gagan
and I think by 25 26 you will have the
first man Mission with maybe two or
three astronauts on board so that will
happen probably by 25 2025 or 2026
probably okay I'm not entirely sure but
hopefully I'm I'm hoping that'll happen
so once that happens successfully it
will demonstrate that India has the the
capability the technology to send humans
into Earth orbit low earth orbit and
bring them back
safely but a lot more
technological uh advancements will need
to be uh
demonstrated successfully before we can
even think of sending humans to the Moon
because that is a way more complex
Mission way more complex and so many
more points of failure we don't want to
lose a life in space we lose lives every
day all across India in accidents in
trains and whatnot but this is a
high-profile thing and if if if single
life is lost the entire country will be
up in
arms so it will have to be done very
very carefully very deliberately very
systematically I think it can be done by
2035 but the government says 2040 plus
so so the first man moon mission will be
earliest in 2040 probably possibly
later but yeah I'm excited about gagan
finally we will have humans in space and
within a decade we could have a
rudimentary space station in Earth orbit
where somebody could stay for an
extended period of time several months
possibly that'll be good progress for us
so I find this very exciting it's very
important for India as a
nation as as as as a world power to be
at the Forefront of space exploration
and space exploration Technologies I
cannot emphasize this strongly enough
it's very important so so we are doing
reasonable progress in that direction I
certainly wish the progress was
accelerated we are certainly capable of
doing much more but this is where we
are adish says do you still play guitar
I my guitar is outside but I don't play
guitar that much anymore I really don't
play guitar at all in these days um
there was a time when I was a really
really good guitar player these days
there's almost no practice so I think my
my skills are kind of rusty right now
but I haven't lost the skill of playing
guitar I can still play play the guitar
uh I think I've played guitar once to
demonstrate an Indian Raga or something
on one of these live streams a year or
two ago so yeah I I still am capable of
playing the guitar maybe I should
reconnect with it if I can find the time
if only I can find the time you see time
is so limited and there's so much to do
especially with somebody like me who has
so many interests and so many things
that I needed to get done so yeah
so I can still play the guitar but I'm
not really playing much these
days Lipton bua says your comments on
the RG car Medical College incident do
you think that girl will ever get
Justice can CBI do it look I typically
don't look at what's happening within
the country when it comes to these
matters I look at geopolitics I look at
things outside the country so with
that as the context I really haven't
looked into detail
looked into the details of what's
happened I know this this terrible
horrible thing that's
happened this this incident which
reminds me of what happened a decade
plus ago the Naya thing horrible and
simply unacceptable in any civilized
society and I don't know what the
situation is whether the culprits have
been identified caught what what's
happening I don't know I am not you know
keeping in touch with what's happening
on a daily basis I just know the outline
of the case so I don't know what the
situation is I prefer not to look into
these matters because it messes up my
mind
okay obviously it's it's absolutely
unacceptable
condemnable and whoever is has done this
should face the fullest extent of of
legal retribution of the law so I don't
know what whether the CBI is involved or
not which agency they're involved I all
I would say is
catch the the
perpetrators and punish them to the
maximum extent Allowed by the law that's
what I would say um it gives India such
a bad name such a bad reputation there
is this perception that India has a very
high incidence of rape India is the rape
Capital which is absolutely untrue India
has one of the lowest incidences of rape
in the world I know there are so many
cases that go unreported the same
happens in the US a fraction of the rape
cases are reported the US most of these
are never reported and yet the US has a
way higher incidence of rape than India
but the media likes to emphasize this
I'm not saying the media should not
cover these cases it is very important
that these cases are covered and it is
more important than that the culprits
are caught and brought to justice
justice needs to be visited on such
people such inhuman barbarians even
animals don't behave like this so that's
my comments on this I don't know much
about the matter because first of all it
it messes my mind to look into these
these matters and I prefer to look at
things outside the country on a
geopolitical level but yes these things
are horrible and they should never
happen
um okay
uh gorov aora welcome thank you for
becoming a member appreciate
it um
okay same matter Again by rajat how can
the Kolkata horror be avoided in the
future seems India is becoming rape
Capital but it is not becoming a rape
Capital but that's the perception that
the media is creating especially the
foreign media uh who is to blame uh you
two son chaa index again okay my the
index will thank you for reminding me
again I think last week also you did
that I'll bring it out very soon it's
it's ready but I just need to prettify
it
make
it make it acceptable for public uh
unveiling anyhow the how can this this
Kolkata horror be avoided what you need
in the
country is Speedy
Justice what you need in the country to
avoid these horrible things is the
guarantee that if somebody breaks the
law then they will be brought to Justice
in a Time bound manner so if you do a
crime it should be almost guaranteed
that that you will be
caught that's what needs to happen right
now unfortunately that's not quite the
case is it there are lots of crimes that
go
unpunished there are lots of crimes in
which the evidence is destroyed
allegedly and so many such things so as
long as you have such a a malfunctioning
system you will have these cases some
horrible individuals will feel that they
can get away with
this so that's what needs to happen
um and yeah
so that that is what India lacks right
now and that's why you have crimes that
happen we need to definitely clamp down
on every every possible crime and the
most effective way of doing that is to
guarantee that if you do a crime you're
going to be caught and you're going to
be punished
swiftly that's a systemic reform that
needs to happen and right now the
systemic reform is not happening and
that's why these cases happen
okay okay let's talk about aliens yeah
yes aliens sham Sharma says what are the
scientific challenges in verifying
claims of extraterrestrial Encounters in
the context of the US government's
historical secrecy and classify the
information so it's been alleged that
the US government has made contact in
the past with
extraterrestrials and they apparently
have alien spacecraft that they are they
have re-engineered or are in the process
of re-engineering there have been
allegations of projects like what
Project Blue Book or something movies
about that TV series TV shows about
that uh little finger was in one of
those TV shows Project Blue Book I
believe and so on so there are all
these uh claims about extraterrestrial
activity and apparently the the aliens
they love the US the most that's that's
that's why they appear in the US the
most right uh now what's the what are
the scientific challenges in verifying
claims of
these phenomena extraterrestrial
encounters Etc it's very simple produce
evidence that that can that is in
controvertible my first question is why
does an alien sighting a UFO sighting
never happen above a crowded City where
like 5,000 people can can take
film and video with their camera with
their cell phone then nobody can deny it
once once 5,000 10,000 people see it and
they all put take out the cell phon and
start filming then nobody can deny this
happen but it's never happened that way
there's not a single case where there
are lots of different pieces of footage
that come out from a thousand different
angles it's always some random event
somewhere and and it's taken by some
some one photographer and the image is
usually
grainy anybody can do that I I can I can
demonstrate that to you I can do it
myself shall I show
you okay let me let me show you what I
can do let's go to my Instagram
account so this is my Instagram account
now if I go back in time to a couple of
years ago where was this I'll show you
an image of UFOs
okay let's go let's go further down
further
down I have an image of UFOs on my own
Instagram
account if I can Discover it here we
have it check it out so this is the this
is the picture I took in ladak this is
this is the pangong lake okay and you
can see a UFO in the sky
and here is another one see it's moved
it seems like it's
moved so this is the quality of images
you get of UFOs now do you know what
this is this is the reflection on glass
of a light it's not a UFO but you can
pretend it's a UFO and people will
believe it okay I was just taking
photographs from my from my cell phone
camera of the lake and its surroundings
from inside the place I was staying and
there was a glass because it's
frighteningly cold out there so you need
you know you need to be inside there's
this glass window from which I'm taking
the pictures and there's lights inside
on the ceiling and this looked like like
a UFO and I put it out as a joke as a
UFO and people started believing it so
that's the thing you know that's the
kind that's the quality of images you're
getting of
UFOs and that's why people are skeptical
so you need evidence that is
incontrovertible you either need a
sighting a mass sighting in which
thousands of people can take images or
even 20 people is
enough or you need actual evidence of an
extraterrestrial spacecraft that that
the government discloses and people can
visit and see can and scientists can
test something like that something that
is scientifically provable that's what
is required and that's not there and
that's why people including me are
skeptical about
this stepen Dominic says why are
scientists only speaking about
terraforming Mars instead of
geoengineering the earth into uh if
humans perhaps go to Mars then the
condition could become like the Earth
polluted and destroyed because of human
evil nature
um so why uh are people like Elon Musk
for example speaking about colonizing
Mars occupying Mars terraforming Mars
it's because
today the situation the technological
level of of various countries is such
that they can destroy the entire
planet we are obviously talking about
nuclear war so the US and Russia have
sufficient nuclear weapons to destroy
the entire planet so it makes sense for
us to have a backup Planet somewhere and
that's why that people talk about going
to Mars and settling there and then
terraforming terraforming the planet
will take time obviously but that's why
they talk about but yes it's possible
that if the same kind of people go to
Mars and they will ruin Mars as well
it's most likely that by the end of this
Century the 21st century at night you
will see lights on on on the moon and
you will have human activity Mining and
all that on the moon and the moon will
become
unrecognizable so yeah well that's just
what it
is lepton bwa says your views on ishat
inonu well that's a name out of the past
interesting so I think ismat you know
was the first leader of turkey after the
the tragic death of Mustafa kimal atat
isi inonu was a soldier he was he served
with Mustafa kamalat in the Turkish war
of independence in 1920s early 1920s and
he was a companion of MFA Kamal Ataturk
he was a very stable bureaucratic kind
of person very very dependable kind of
person
andat clearly trusted him and after the
death of atat isi inonu became the
leader of turkey so that's what I can
say about him
weall reasonably good guy I would say
good soldier as
well um myuri says what are your
thoughts on Malcolm X do his opinions or
ideologies reservate with you I haven't
really studied Malcolm X and his and his
writings his sayings his ideology Etc I
haven't really studed did that uh
obviously Black Power movement and and
and so on all that was there yes uh
clearly uh so he was involved in that
1950s 1960s he was one of the prominent
uh leaders of the black community in the
US uh but I am not very familiar with
his ideology Etc so I'm not really sure
if I am in a position to answer that
right now see you see I I haven't
studied everything in the
world yeah
ragav says which language was spoken by
the turo mugal Kings so initially it was
the chagatai language people like who
was the first individual to to enter
India it was it was it was Babar right
zahin Babar so he clearly spoke the
chagatai tur language and later by the
time orze was ruling uh certain parts of
India I think the language spoken was
was Persian Persian because orang zeb's
mother was mumtaz right Shah jahan's
Shah Jan's wife and she was Persian so
yeah there was a transition from the
turkic languages to to Persian so the
turkic language was most likely chagatai
which no longer is extinct today it's an
extinct language but it was spoken in
the second Millennium ad and it it went
out of existence later
on
um shaswat says show some light on the
life of rash bihari Bose once again
that's another historical figure that I
have not studied in great detail there
are many historical figures that I have
not studied Dr edar I know next to
nothing about him I've never studied his
life his writings whatever same with
rash bihari B same with malol X there
are many people whose life I've not
studied so yeah obviously he's one of
the important figures in the Indian
revolutionary movement closely
associated with Japan I think he he had
a Japanese wife and so on but uh beyond
that I would not be able to tell you
much at this stage in time I would I
would read up about him to be able to
answer this question in in any
detail so yeah there you have
it
now
um pran Q2 says who is raama lakmi RA I
have never met ramal lakmi I've never
spoken with ramal lakmi but I am so
grateful to Ram lakmi because because he
puts out the timestamps for every live
stream without fail it is such a
tremendous service he has doing to the
entire community of viewers of this
Channel and to me also because it it uh
well it it's such a big help so I am I
don't know I would love
to reach out and meet ramal lakmi one of
these days and express my gratitude in
person but all I can say is Rama lakmi
thank you very much I'm extremely
grateful for everything you do
really really appreciate
that okay I think we have crossed two
hours and 10
minutes
um maybe I can take one or two more
questions arav says who are what are
what are some of your favorite science
books my science books are the dangerous
ones that are full
of full of equations for of problems I
see these books here some of these books
are the Sham series books on various
topics which I worked through as a
student extremely valuable books
indispensable if you want to really
Master a subject because it's not enough
to just read theory in all in textbooks
you have to work through
problems hundreds of problems so the
Sham series books are great when it
comes to studying and learning various
aspects of physics or science I'm sure
they have sham series books on chemistry
and biology and whatnot also so the sh
series books uh one of my favorite books
on mathematical physics is the one by
Mary
boss um it's it's it's a pretty it's one
of the first mathematical physics books
you will work through
um what
else the quantum mechanics book by SED
flug is one of my favorites it's the
book that separates the men from the
boys so to say you know want to read do
quantum mechanics you work through the
problems in the in the book by fluk G
and that book is probably out of print
by now tremendous book so I I don't read
popular science books I have a few here
and there but I don't
really really read them not very fond of
those I have a couple of books by uh
Kaku Muk Kaku and I have some some some
popular science books but overall my
favorite science books are the are the
rigorous scientific books the books when
from which you can actually
will gain new knowledge and do actual
research okay let's take maybe one last
question okay this this is the last
question for today Shri VR says how to
enjoy uncertain times in life look the
way to enjoy uncertain times in life is
to worry about what you can control and
don't think about what you can control
because it is beyond your control you
should be aware of what the world is
like and what are the things that are
beyond your control the environment Al
factors that you don't control you
should be aware of them you should plan
for all possible outcomes that are
potentially that potentially could to
happen but worry about only the things
that you can control and those things
you do well and overall be positive be
optimistic be cheerful and try to enjoy
everything you do and have some fun
every day that's how you enjoy uncertain
times in life and obviously you work
hard the harder you work the more you
can enjoy the fun times so that's what I
would
say and with that I'm going to end
today's live stream I can see many more
interesting questions but I'm going to
end it here because we' have crossed Way
Beyond two hours so thank you so much
for all your questions and I will see
you in tomorrow's live stream thank you
very much take care keep asking
questions and keep raising your
standards every single day keep
improving yourselves thank you and I'll
see you in tomorrow's live stream bye